第七封印
THE SEVENTH SEAL
【和合本 启示录8:1】
羔羊揭开第七印的时候……
Ad wen the Lamb opened the seventh seal -
天上寂静……
- there was in heaven a silence -
约有二刻
- which lasted about the space of half an hour.
【和合本 启示录8:6】
拿着七枝号的七位天使……
And the seven angels who had the seven trumpets -
就预备要吹
- prepared themselves to sound.
- 你是谁？ - 我是死神
- Who are you? - I a Death.
- 你是来取走我魂魄的吗？
- 我已经伴随在你左右很久了
- Have you come to fetch me? - I have long walked at your side.
- 我知道 - 你准备好了吗？
- That I know. - Are you ready?
我的身体已经准备好了 但是我的心却没有
My body is, not myself.
- 等一下 - 你们都这么说
- Wait a moment. - You all say that.
- 但是我不会等的 - 你下象棋，对吗？
- But I leave no respite. - You play chess, don't you?
- 你怎么知道？ - 从画和民歌中知道的
- How do you know? - From paintings and folk songs.
是的，我是个真正的象棋高手
Yes, I'm actually quite a skillful chess player.
- 不会比我强 - 那我们何不比试比试？
- Not more so than me. - Why play chess with me?
- 正有此意 - 很好
- That's my affair. - You are right.
条件是在和你下棋时我得活着
The condition is I live as long as I resist you.
如果我赢了，你就放了我
If I conquer you, you free me.
你执黑
You have black.
再合适不过了，不是吗？
It's most appropriate, not so?
碾碎那些在床第间的叹息
Squeezed twixt the thighs on a bed of sighs
那是成为像我一样的男子汉
That's the only way to be
的唯一方式
For a man like me
我们的君主高高在上 他有一些害羞
Our Lord sits up high He is somewhat shy
但是撒旦，你的亲信 确保你不会孤单
But Satan, your crony ensures you won't be Ionely
他们谈到了在Farjestad 发生的一些可怕的事情
They talk of omens and other horrors in Farjestad.
昨晚有两匹马吃掉了另一匹马
Two horses ate one another last night.
墓地里的墓穴被打开了 遗骨到处散落
Graves had been opened in the cemetery and remains scattered about.
昨天下午天空中出现了四个太阳
There were four suns in the heavens yesterday afternoon.
你能告诉我去旅馆的路怎么走吗？
Can you tell me the way to the inn?
- 他说了怎么走了吗？ - 没有
- Did he indicate the way? - Not exactly.
- 他说了什么？ - 什么也没说
- What did he say? - Nothing.
- 他是哑巴吗？ - 不，不能那么说
- Was he dumb? - No, one can't say that.
我得说他非常善言
I'd say that he was extremely well-spoken.
是的，非常善言 但是不得不承认他的话非常严肃
Yes, well-spoken. But the speech he made was dour. I have to say.
早晨好，你吃早饭了吗？
Good morning. Have you had any breakfast?
真不幸，我不能吃草 为什么你不教教我呢？
Unfortunately, I can't eat grass. Can't you teach me?
手头紧了，这些地方的人 对艺术都不感兴趣
Things are tight. People aren't interested in art in these parts.
米亚，起来！ 我必须告诉你我看见了什么
Mia, wake up! I've seen something I must tell you about.
- 出什么事了？ - 我刚才出现了幻觉
- Has something happened? - I've had a vision.
不，不是幻觉，那和真的一样
No, not a vision. It was like it was real.
知道了…你又有幻觉了
I see... Have you had another vision?
总之，我看到她了
I saw her, anyway.
- 谁，你看到谁了？ - 圣母玛利亚
- Who? Who did you see? - The Holy Virgin Mary.
- 真的？ - 她近得我都可以摸到她
- Really? - She was so close I could touch her.
她头戴金冠，身上披着蓝色的花衣
She had a crown of gold and a blue dress with flowers -
她赤着脚，皮肤微黑
- and she was barefoot and had small brown hands.
她牵着那个小孩，教他走路
She held the child and taught him to walk.
她看到我看她，还对我笑
Then she saw that I'd seen her and she smiled at me.
我的眼中充满了泪水，当我 擦去它们时，她消失了
I got tears in my eyes and when I wiped them away, she disappeared.
到处都变得非常非常宁静
And it became utterly, utterly quiet everywhere.
无论天空还是大地 你能想象吗？
In heaven and on earth. Can you understand that?
- 你出现了幻觉 - 你不相信我，但那是真的
- You have an imagination. -You don't believe me, but it was real.
不是你所说的那种真实 而是另一种
Not your kind of reality, but another reality.
就像你上次说魔鬼用它的尾巴 把我们的马车轮子涂成红色一样
Like when you said the Devil painted our wagon wheels red using his tail.
提那个干什么？
Why bring that up?
- 你的指甲里就有红色颜料 - 对，那次是假的
- Red paint was under your nails. - Yes, that time it was made up.
我那样做是为了要你相信 我所看到的真实景象
I did it so you'd believe in my other visions. The real ones.
控制一下你的幻想吧 不然别人会把你当傻瓜看
Control your visions, or you'll be taken for a fool - which you aren't.
起码到现在，没人知道这些
At least not yet, as far as I know. But one never knows.
我那不是幻想！ 我不可能让圣女来救赎
I didn't ask for my visions! I can't help the Holy Virgin revealing herself -
还有那些天使，魔鬼 喜欢和我呆在一起
- and that angels and devils like to be with me.
我不止一次说过早上我需要睡觉！
Haven't I said it once and for all that I need to sleep in the morning?
我要求你，我请求你 但是一点用也没有
I've asked you, begged you, but nothing helps.
所以我现在要说…安静！
That's why I'm now saying... quiet!
米克尔，米克尔，米克尔…
Mikael, Mikael, Mikael...
- 他该过的比我们好
- 米克尔将来会是个伟大的杂技演员
- He should have a better life than us. - Mikael will be a great acrobat.
或许是一个伟大的魔术师 会变最不可思议的戏法
Or maybe a juggler who accomplishes the only impossible trick.
- 什么样的戏法？ - 让一个球悬浮在空中
- What trick is that? - Make one ball remain still in the air.
- 那不可能
- 对我们来说不可能，但他可以
- It's impossible. - For us it is. But not for him.
你的白日梦…
You and your fantasies...
我昨晚又作了一首新歌 几乎整晚没睡
I made up a new song last night. I lay awake almost all night.
- 你想听听吗？ - 唱吧，我很想听
- Do you want to hear my song? - Sing it. I'm really curious.
一只鸽子栖息在盛夏的百合上
There sits a dove on the lilly In the midst of summer
她唱着赞美基督的美妙歌曲
She sings her fair song of Jesus Christ
天堂如此的欢喜
There is great rejoicing in heaven
- 米亚，你睡着了吗？ - 这歌很美
- Mia, are you asleep? - It was a very beautiful song.
- 我还没唱完呢 - 我只是稍微有点困了
- It's not finished yet. - I'm just going to sleep a little more.
- 你可以晚点再唱剩下的部分 - 你除了睡就是睡
- You can sing the rest later. - You just sleep and sleep.
这个装扮怎么样？ 我就是问问
Is this disguise worthy of an actor? I'm only asking.
- 如果牧师不给钱，我就不干了 - 你演死神吗？
- If the priests didn't pay, I'd refuse. - Are you playing Death?
吓吓那些有钱的体面人
Frighten decent people out of their wits with such nonsense.
- 什么时候？
- 在EIsinore的All Saints节日上
- When are we going to do it? - At the All Saints festival in Elsinore.
就在教堂前的台阶上，还不赖
On the actual church steps. Not bad.
为什么不是些艳舞之类的？
人们喜欢看而且也有意思
Why not something bawdy? People like it and it's funnier.
傻瓜，那里现在瘟疫蔓延
Idiot. There's an evil sickness about -
牧师要宣讲严肃的死亡和信仰的问题
- and priests are preaching grim death and moral bellyaches.
- 我们演什么？ - 你们演人的灵魂
- What roles will we play? - You're the human soul, you twit.
- 说真的，那是个坏角色 - 谁决定的？谁是老板？
- Naturally it's a bad role. - Who decides? Who's the manager?
你们这些傻瓜，忘掉那些规矩吧 生命的细线是非常脆弱的
You fools, keep this law in mind Life's thread is of the weakest kind
你们会发现生命很短暂
Life is short, you will find
女人们会喜欢我这种打扮吗？ 我就是问问
Will women love me in this costume? I'm only asking.
约瑟夫，别说话 什么也别说
Jof? Stand perfectly still. Don't say anything.
- 我安静的像只老鼠 - 我爱你…
- I'm quiet as a mouse. - I love you...
- 你在画什么？ - 死神的舞蹈
- What are you painting? - The dance of Death.
-那是死神吗？
-是的，他一边跳舞一边带走他们所有人
-That's Death?
-Yes, he dances away with them all.
- 为什么画这些？
- 提醒人们他们就要死了
- Why paint such daubings? - To remind people they will die.
- 那不会使他们高兴的
- 为什么总要取悦他们呢？
- That won't make them happier. - Why always make them happy?
- 为何不吓吓他们
- 他们最多闭上眼就行了
- Why not frighten them a bit? - They'll just close their eyes then.
相信我，他们一定会看的 一个头骨远比通奸更有吸引力
Believe me, they'll look. A skull is more interesting than a naked wench.
- 如果吓到他们呢？
- 他们就会越想越害怕
- And if you frighten them? - They'll think and be more frightened.
- 然后扑进牧师的怀抱 - 这我不管
- And rush into the priest's embrace. - Not my business.
- 你只画死神的舞蹈
- 我只是想展示那是怎么样的
- You're just painting Death's dance. - I'm only showing how it is.
- 你会惹恼一些人的
- 那么我会再画些轻松的
- You'll anger certain people. - Then I'll paint something cheerful.
人总是要活命的 至少在瘟疫找到你之前是的
One has to make a living. At least until the plague claims you.
瘟疫？可怕的…
The plague? That's horrifying...
你可以看到那些病人脖子上的疖子
You should see the boil on the neck of the sick.
看看他们是怎样感染的
See how the body contracts, until his limbs become a rope of madness.
- 看上去糟透了 - 是啊…糟透了
- It doesn't look good. - Yes... It doesn't look good.
他试图撕裂他自己
He's trying to tear the bubo out of his bed.
他咬自己的手 用指甲撕开皮肤
He gnaws at his hands, rips out his veins with his nails.
他的尖叫随处可闻
His scream is heard everywhere.
- 你害怕了吗？ - 害怕？我？
- Are you scared? - Scared? Me?
你不了解我，那些是什么东西？
You don't know me. What nonsense is that you've painted?
那些是说人们认为…
The strange thing is that people see -
瘟疫是上帝降临的惩罚
- the plague as a punishment from God.
那些病人一路走一路鞭打自己 以祈求上帝的怜悯
Supplicants trail through the land and whip themselves into God's favour.
- 他们打自己？ - 是的，看上去太糟了
- They beat themselves? - Yes, it's an awful sight.
当他们走过来时你就想躲开
You want to run and hide when they come.
能打断一下吗？ 我今天一直在喝水
Have you got any snaps? I've been drinking water all day.
- 我就像只沙漠中的骆驼一样干渴 - 你有些害怕了
- I'm thirsty as a camel in the desert. - You did get a little scared, after all.
我想尽可能坦诚地忏悔 但是我的心空空如也
I want to confess as honestly as I can, but my heart is empty.
空虚就像我面前的一面镜子
And emptiness is a mirror turned to my own face.
我看到了我自己… 我被厌恶和恐惧所俘获
I see myself... and am seized by disgust and fear.
由于我对人民的漠不关心 我已被排斥在社会之外
Through my indifference for people, I've been placed outside of their society.
现在我生活在一个幽灵的世界 我的梦境和思想都被占据
Now I live in a ghost world, enclosed in my dreams and imaginings.
- 不管怎样，你不想死 - 是的，我不想
- Despite that, you don't want to die. - Yes, I want to.
- 你在期待什么？ - 我需要知识
- What are you waiting for? - I want knowledge.
- 你想要保证 - 随便你怎么说
- You want guarantees. - Call it what you like.
仅凭一人的感觉想去 理解上帝的意图真的这么难吗？
Is it so terribly inconceivable to comprehend God with one's senses?
为什么他总藏在半真半假的承诺 和从未实现过的奇迹背后呢？
Why does He hide in a cloud of half-promises and unseen miracles?
当我们缺乏信仰的时候 又如何守信呢？
How can we believe in the faithful when we lack faith?
我们将会怎样，谁会去相信？
What will happen to us who want to believe, but cannot?
难道要相信那些我们 不想也不能相信的事情吗？
What about those who neither want to nor can believe?
为什么我不能杀死心中的上帝？
Why can't I kill God in me?
为何他使我蒙羞？
Why does He live on in me in an humiliating way -
尽管我想要把他从我心中抹去
- despite my wanting to evict Him from my heart?
为什么他总像一个 我无法摆脱的嘲笑者？
Why is He despite all, a mocking reality I can't be rid of?
- 你在听吗？ - 我在听
- Do you hear? - I hear you.
我需要真理！不是信仰 不是承诺，而是真理
I want knowledge! Not faith, not assumptions, but knowledge.
我希望上帝能伸出他的手 露出他的脸，和我说话
I want God to stretch out His hand, uncover His face and speak to me.
- 但是他仍然沉默 - 我在黑暗中呼唤他
- But He remains silent. - I call out to Him in the darkness.
- 但似乎没有人在那里 - 或许那没有任何人
- But it's as if no one was there. - Perhaps there isn't anyone.
那么生命真是荒诞而可怕
Then life is a preposterous horror.
没有人可以活着面对死神 了解一切都是虚幻的
No man can live faced with Death, knowing everything's nothingness.
大部分人认为既没有死神也没有虚幻
Most people think neither of Death nor nothingness.
但是有一天当你站在生死边缘
But one day you stand at the edge of life and face darkness.
- 那一天 - 我明白你的意思
- That day. - I understand what you mean.
我们必须构筑一个对抗恐惧的偶像
We must make an idol of our fear -
而那个偶像我们称之为上帝
- and that idol we shall call God.
你太多虑了
You are worried.
死神今早来看我，我们一起下了象棋
Death came to see me this morning. We played chess together.
我所学到的东西使我能完成一些事
The grace I received allows me to accomplish something.
我的一生都在寻找、希望…
All my life I've been searching, wondering -
没有目的和利害关系的交谈
- talking without meaning or context.
但一无所获。
我这样说 没有苦闷和自责的意思
It has been nothing. Yes, I say so without bitterness or self-reproach -
因为我知道大部分人的人生都是如此
- as I know that almost all of people's lives are made this way.
但是我想用这余下的生命 做点有意义的事情
But I want to use my respite for one meaningful act.
那就是为什么你要和死神下象棋
That's why you are playing chess with the Devil.
他很有谋略和技巧 但是到现在我还没有输一个子
He's a difficult and skillful tactician, but so far I have not surrended a piece.
你怎么能在游戏中蒙骗死神？
How can you outwit the Devil in your game?
我移动了国王和骑士
I'm playing a combination of bishop and knight -
他没有发现，下一手 就可以让他的侧翼暴露出来
- that he hasn't noticed yet. I'll expose his flank in the next move.
我会记住的
I'll remember that.
你是个叛徒…你欺骗了我
You're a traitor... and you cheated me.
但是我们还会见面 我会想到方法的
But we'll meet again. And I'll find a way.
我们会在旅馆见面 继续我们的棋局
We'll meet at the inn. We'll continue our game then.
这是我的手，我可以控制它…
This is my hand. I can move it...
我的血液涌入其中
My blood gushes in it.
太阳还高高挂在天上…
The sun is still high in the sky...
而我…我，安东尼斯.布莱克
And I... I, Antonius Block...
要和死神下棋
...am playing chess with the Devil.
我主人和我一直在国外
My master and I have been abroad.
你知道吗？我亲爱的…皮克多
Do you understand, my dear... Pictor?
- 十字军 - 正是
- The crusades. - Exactly.
整整10年 蛇咬我们…
For 10 years we let snakes bite us -
昆虫蛰我们，动物袭击我们 野蛮人屠杀我们
- insects sting us, animals maul us, heathens slaughter us -
酒毒害我们，女人影响我们 虱子以我们为食，炎热使我们腐烂…
- the wine poison us, women infect us, lice eat us, fever rot us...
- 所有这一切，以上帝的名义 - 以上帝的名义
- Everything... in the name of God. - In the name of God.
十字军东征真是个愚蠢的主意 只有空想家才想得出
Our crusade was so stupid, only an idealist could have invented it.
- 就像这场瘟疫一样可怕 - 比那还槽
- All this about the plague is awful. - It's worse than that.
哦，也许… 你总是坐在你的屁股上
Oh, yes... It's always your own arse you sit on.
- 一个伟大的真理 - 你的屁股
- A great truth. - Your own arse. Your own arse.
- 一个深刻的真理 - 这是乔恩的乡绅
- A profound truth... - Here is Jons the squire.
他对着死神大笑，嘲笑君主 讥笑自己，对女孩们微笑
He grins at Death, guffaws at the Lord, laughs at himself, smiles at the girls.
他的世界里没有什么值得相信
――除了他自己
His world is believable to no one but himself.
每个人都是荒谬的甚至他自己
Ridiculous to everyone, even himself.
无论天堂或是地狱 都是无关紧要，无意义的…
Meaningless in heaven and indifferent in hell...
你的酒坛很臭，怎么回事？
Your stew stinks, what's it for?
她很邪恶
She was joined in flesh with the Evil One.
- 现在她被抓起来了 - 她会在早上被烧死
- And now she's in the stocks. - She will burn in the morning.
- 但是我们必须要驱走魔鬼
- 用这些臭气熏天的东西吗？
- But we must keep the Devil away. - With that stinking brew?
最好的原料： 一只大黑狗的血
The best stuff; blood and guts of a big black dog.
邪恶的家伙不能忍受这味道
The... the Evil One can't bear the smell.
我也不能
Me neither.
你看到魔鬼了吗？
Have you seen the Devil?
- 别和她说话 - 有那么危险吗？
- Don't talk to her? - Is it so dangerous?
我不知道，可是她看起来 会把瘟疫带给我们
I don't know, but she's seen as guilty of the plague that has befallen us.
Oh, fate is a reprobate You my friend an unfortunate
Now you bound in haste Now worms lay you to waste
- 你非唱不可吗？ - 不是…
- Must you sing? - No...
为什么你那么惊讶的样子？ 因为我从死人手上偷东西？
Why do you look so surprised? I steal from the dead.
这几天收获很不错
It's quite a rewarding domain these days.
你想去告发我吗？没用的
You're thinking of telling tales in the village? It won't help.
每个人现在都自身难保 非常简单
Each one of us saves his own skin. It's that simple.
别想叫，没有人会听到 上帝也不会
Don't try to scream. No one will hear you, neither God nor man.
这没什么好惊讶的
It's nothing to be surprised about.
我认识你 尽管已经很久了
I recognize you, even though it was long ago.
你是瑞沃 从Roskilde的神学院来的
You're Raval from the seminary in Roskilde.
我说的对吗？
Mirabilis,Caelestis et Diabilis Doctor Mirabilis, Caelestis et Diabilis. Am I not right?
你鼓动我的主人去参加神圣的十字军
You convinced my master to go to the Holy Land on an honourable crusade.
看上去你不开心？
Are you worried? Butterflies in your belly?
现在我想这10年是毫无意义的浪费
Now I understand the meaning of these 1 0 years that I thought wasted.
我们已经受够了
We had it too good, we were too content.
主想惩罚我们的自满
The Lord wanted to punish our self-satisfied pride.
他要你来用毒液毒害骑士
He sent you to spit your heavenly venom and to poison the knight.
- 那是美好的信仰
- 但是现在就更好了，不是吗？
- It was in good faith. - But now you know better, not so?
现在你是一个贼，对你 这种坏人再合适不过的职业
Now you're a thief, a more suitable occupation for wretches and villains.
我说的不对吗？
Am I not right?
不管怎么说，我不是个嗜杀的人
By all means. I am not bloodthirsty.
下次我会在你的脸上做个记号 像对其他和你一样的小人做的一样
Next time I'll mark your face like we do with petty villains of your kind.
事实上我是来盛水的
I actually came to fill my water bag.
我叫乔恩，我是个健谈的…
Jons is the name. I'm a nice, talkative young man -
思想端正，行为高尚的年轻人
- who only thinks good thoughts and commits honourable deeds.
再见，姑娘… 我其实可以强迫你
Farewell, my girl... I could have raped you.
但是我希望我们之间能有爱情 虽然那在我心中已经干涸很久了
But between us, I'm tired of that kind of love. It's dry in the long run.
特别是当我需要一个女管家时 你的厨艺好吗？
When I think of it I need a housekeeper. Do you cook well?
我结婚了，但是我希望 我老婆最好现在就死
I'm married, but I have hope my wife will be dead by now.
所以我需要一个女管家
So I need a housekeeper!
别光站在那，过来 我救了你，你欠我的
Come now and don't just stand there. I saved you from death so you owe me!
真是差劲…
Bloody hams...
简直像小丑
Making a spectacle of themselves.
住手，你们这些蠢猪
Stop that, you tin-heads!
我不演了！
I don't start so I'll go behind the drape.
不演了，你们这些笨蛋！
Stop staring, you blockheads!
The horse sits in the tree and crows
The road is wide but the door is low The Black One dances on the beach
The hen miaows in the darkest lake
The day is red but the fish is dead
The Black One squats on the beach
The snake flutters in heaven's heights
The virgin is pale but the pussy shows delight
The Black One runs on the beach
The ram hisses with teeth apart
The gust is harsh and the waves dart
The Black One farts on the beach
The horse sits in the tree and crows
The road is wide but the door is low
The Black One dances on the beach
The hen miaows in the darkest lake
The day is red but the fish is dead
The Black One squats on the beach
The snake flutters in heaven's heights
The virgin is pale but the pussy shows delight
The Black One runs on the beach
The sow lays and the cat sows
Night is blighted and darkness glows
The Black One remains, remains
Remains, remains on the beach
上帝让惩罚降临在我们身上
God has sent His punishment over us.
是的！你们所有人都会消失…
Yes! You will all vanish...
…陷入黑色的死亡
...by the Black Death.
你们就像等待屠宰的牛群
You standing there like open-mouthed cattle.
而你们却还满足于现状
And you sitting there in bloated self-satisfaction.
你们知道这可能是 你们生命的最后一点时间吗？
Do you know that this could be your final hour?
死神就在你们身后
Death stands behind you.
我可以看到他头上的阴影 遮蔽了太阳
I can see the crown of his head gleam in the sun.
当他在你们的身后举起亮闪闪的长镰时
His scythe flashes when he raises it behind your heads.
你们之中谁会被他第一个选中？
Who among you will he strike first?
你们就像是替罪的羔羊
You there, staring like a goat...
在天黑之前是否已经死去？
Before evening will your mouth be distorted into a last, unfinished yawn?
至于你，姑娘 青春亮丽，活力四射
And you, woman... Blooming with appetite and lust for life...
是否会在黎明前已经变得苍白无力？
Will you grow pale and drop before the dawn?
而你这个长着大鼻子一脸傻笑的家伙…
And you there with your swollen nose and silly grin...
你是不是还有一年的时间 用自己的尸体污染这土地？
Have you got a year left to pollute the earth with your debris?
你们这些傻瓜知不知道 你们所有人都会死？
Do you know, you confirmed idiots, that you are all going to die?
今天，明天，或者后天 你们所有人都有罪
Today, tomorrow, or the next day. You are all condemned.
你们听到我的话了吗？听到了吗？ 有罪，有罪！
Do you hear what I say? Do you hear the word? Condemned, condemned!
主啊，怜悯我们这些下等人吧
Lord, take pity on us in our degradation.
不要弃我们于不顾
Don't turn Your face from us in contempt -
怜悯我们吧，怜悯你的子民，耶稣基督
- but have mercy on us for the sake of your Son, Jesus Christ!
这有关厄运的演说真是血腥 这就是有思想的人维持生计的方式吗？
This bloody talk of doom. Is that sustenance for a modern man?
他们真以为我们会认真对待吗？ 你在嘲笑我，先生
Do they really think we'll take them seriously? You laugh at me, Sire.
我读过，听过，经历过很多的事情
I've read, heard and experienced most stories we tell one another.
甚至是有关精灵，基督和圣灵的…
Even the ghost story of God, Jesus Christ and the Holy Spirit -
我已经麻木了
- I've absorbed without much emotion.
- 你叫什么？ - 我是普洛，你是乔恩吗？
- Why are you shouting? - I'm Plog and you're Jons.
- 可能吧 - 你见过我妻子吗？
- That's possible. - Have you seen my wife?
不，没有，就算有 她如果像你，我也会很快忘记
No, I haven't. But if I had, and she resembled you, I'd be quick to forget.
- 那么你没见过她？ - 大概她跑了吧
- So, you haven't seen her? - Maybe she's run away.
- 那你知道一些？
- 很多，但没有关于你妻子的
- Do you know anything? - Quite a lot, but not of your wife.
去酒馆看看，或许能有收获
Go to the tavern and you may find an answer.
那是真的，瘟疫蔓延整个西海岸 人们就像蚊虫一样死去
It's true, the plague has swamped the west coast. People die like flies.
生意在这种时候还是不错 但是我的库存还没有脱手
Business is normally good at this time of year, but my stock's unsold.
他们都在谈论末日 所有的预兆都很可怕
They talk of the Last Day. And all the omens certainly are terrible.
一个女人生出了一个牛头
A woman gave birth to a calf's head.
人们都疯狂了，他们逃往内地 把瘟疫也带了过去
People are crazy. They flee inland and take the plague with them.
如果真的是那样，我们 真该庆幸我们还能站着的日子
If it's as they say, then we'll have to enjoy life as long as we're standing.
很多人都死了
Many people have cleaned themselves by fire and died.
但是牧师说死了总好过活在地狱
But the priest says it is better to die clean than to live for hell.
这是末日，我们都知道 只是不敢这样说罢了
This is the end, that's what it is. We all know it, but no one dares to say it.
这是末日，人们因为恐惧而疯狂
This is the end. People are crazy with fear.
- 你也怕了吗？ - 你说的太对了，我怕！
- And you're scared too? - Too right I'm scared!
审判日的黄昏
Judgement Day edges toward evening.
天使降临，坟墓敞开 那真是可怕的景象
The angels descend and the graves open. It will be terrible to see.
- 这个手镯便宜卖你 - 我买不起
- I'll sell you this bracelet cheaply. - I can't afford it.
- 这是纯银的
- 是很漂亮，但是恐怕太贵了
- It's genuine silver. - It's nice, but probably too expensive.
- 你们看到过我妻子吗？ - 她失踪了吗？
- Have you gentlemen seen my wife? - Is she lost?
他们说她和一个演员跑了
She's run away, they say. With an actor.
一个演员？
如果她的品味这么差，就随她去好了
An actor? If she has such bad taste, let her go.
你说的很对 我刚还想杀了她
You are absolutely right. I was thinking I would kill her.
- 我知道，可杀人是另一回事了 - 我还要杀了那个演员
- I see. Murder is another thing. - I'm going to kill the actor, too.
- 演员？ - 那个把她拐跑的家伙
- The actor? - The one she's run off with.
- 为什么？ - 你有毛病吗？
- What for? - Are you thick?
哦，那个演员！我知道 他们现在应该已经走很远了
Oh, the actor! Now I understand. There are far too many of them.
就算他没错，你也要杀他？
Even if he's blameless, you should kill him.
- 你在给他讲故事吗？ - 我？讲故事？
- Are you telling tales to him? - Me? Am I telling tales?
你也是演员，说不定你和他同谋
You're also an actor and it's your cronie that's snuck off with his wife.
你也是演员吗？
Are you an actor as well?
我，演员？不是
Me, an actor? Not really.
那我们会杀了你
Then we should kill you. It's logical.
- 你很有意思 - 你死定了
- You're funny. - You've gone pale.
- 你不会觉得良心不安吗？ - 你很有意思，不是吗？
- Something on your conscience? - You're funny. Don't you think so?
或许我们该在你的脸上 做个坏人的记号
Maybe we should mark you as one does with petty villains of your kind.
你对我妻子干了什么？
What have you done to my wife?
你想杀了我吗？为什么？
Do you want to hurt me? Why?
我在这里碍事吗？ 我最好还是走，不会再来了
Have I annoyed anyone or been in the way? I'll leave and never come back.
站起来，让所有人都能听到你
Stand up so everyone can hear you.
大声点…
Speak louder...
倒立，让我们看看你是不是好演员
Stand on your head so we can see whether you're a good actor.
你对我妻子做了什么？
What have you done to my wife?
- 别想跑，起来跳舞 - 我不，我不
- Don't whimper. Get up and dance. - I can't. I won't.
- 学狗熊的样子 - 我不会模仿
- Imitate a bear. - I can't imitate a bear.
让我们看看
We'll see if you can anyway.
- 起来，当头好熊 - 我不会演熊
- Get up. Be a good bear. - I can't be a bear anymore.
记着下次我们再见到你 会狠狠的收拾你
Remember what I'd do to you if we met again?
我是个守信用的人
I'm a man of my word.
- 他叫什么？ - 米克尔
- What's his name? - Mikael.
- 他多大？ - 刚满一岁
- How old is he? - He's just over one year.
- 他看起来比实际年龄大些 - 你这么想吗？他是挺大的
- He's big for his age. - You think so? Yes, he is quite big.
- 你今天表演了 - 你认为那很糟糕吗？
- You were in a performance today. - Did you think it was bad?
你没化妆看起来更漂亮 这件衣服很适合你
You're more beautiful without make-up. That dress suits you better.
你这么想吗？乔纳森离开了 所以现在我们的情况真是糟
You think so? Jonas Skat went and left us, so now we're in a real fix.
- 他是你丈夫吗？ - 乔纳森？不是
- Is that your husband? - Jonas? No.
- 我丈夫叫约瑟夫 - 哦，他
- The other man is. His name is Jof. - Oh, him.
现在只有我和他 我们还得演出，真是无聊
Now it's only me and him. We'll have to do tricks again, and that's a bother.
- 你也演出吗？ - 哦，是的，而且约瑟夫很会变戏法
- Do you do tricks as well? - Oh, yes. And Jof is a good juggler.
- 米克尔将来还会是个杂耍演员吗？ - 约瑟夫这样希望
- Will Mikael also be an acrobat? - Jof wants him to be.
- 但是你不想？ - 我不知道
- But not you? - I don't know.
- 或许他会是个骑士 - 那可不太好玩，要我说的话
- Maybe he'll be a knight. - It's not so much fun, I can tell you.
- 你看来不高兴 - 没有
- You don't look happy. - No.
- 你很累吗？为什么？
- 我已经厌倦了我的同伴
- Are you tired? Why? - I have boring company.
- 你是说你的随从？ - 不，不是他
- Do you mean your squire? - No, not him.
- 那你说的是谁？ - 我自己
- Who do you mean, then? - Myself.
- 哦，我知道了 - 你真的知道吗?
- Oh, I understand. - Do you really?
是的，我非常理解
Yes, I understand quite well.
我常常想为什么人们总是折磨自己
I often wonder why people torment themselves as soon as they can.
- 米亚… - 约瑟夫…约瑟夫，怎么了？
- Mia... - Jof... Jof, what is it?
约瑟夫！约瑟夫！你怎么了？ 你…快点坐下吧
Jof! Jof, what have you done? Have you...? Come and sit down.
你去哪了？让我看看
Where have you been? Let me look at you.
为什么你非去酒馆不可？ 你喝醉了
Why did you have to go to the tavern? You drank, of course.
- 我没有喝多 - 你老是说什么天使魔鬼之类的
- I didn't drink a drop. - You boasted about angels and devils.
- 人们不喜欢太多的想法 - 我没有提起天使啊
- People don't like too many ideas. - I didn't mention angels.
那么你唱歌跳舞了 你总是表演
Then you sang and danced. You always have to perform.
- 然后他们就生气了 - 你看…
- People get angry at that, too. - Look at what...
看看…看看我给你带什么来了？
Look at what... at what I bought for you.
- 你买不起的 - 反正我弄到了
- You couldn't afford that. - Well, I did it anyway.
约瑟夫！
Jof!
- 哦，他们出手真重 - 为什么你不回手？
- Oh, they gave me such a beating. - Why didn't you give one back?
我只会害怕和生气 但不会很久
I just got scared and angry, but never got that far.
我生气了，相信我 我像狮子一样咆哮…
I got angry, believe me. I roared like a lion...
- 他们害怕了？ - 没有，他们都在笑
- Did they get scared? - No, they just laughed.
米克尔…米克尔
Mikael... Mikael.
- 他身上的味道很好闻 - 而且他很结实
- Smell how good he smells. - And he's solid.
你是个棒小伙 绝对是个杂耍演员的料
You're a solid one, you are. A real acrobat's body.
这是我丈夫，约瑟夫
This is my husband, Jof.
- 你好 - 你好
- Good day. - Good day.
你有个很可爱的儿子 他带给你们很多乐趣
You have a fine son. He will bring you joy.
是的，他很可爱 我们有些什么可招待的，米亚？
Yes, he is lovely. Do we have anything to offer, Mia?
- 谢谢，不需要了 - 我摘了些野草莓
- Thanks, I shan't have anything. - I picked wild strawberries.
- 而且还挤了些牛奶 - 有牛奶…
- And we actually milked some milk. - Have milked...
如果骑士大人能和我们 一同进餐那真是荣幸万分
If the knight would join us it would be an honour.
- 请坐吧，我去拿吃的 - 请…
- Sit down and I'll bring the food. - Please...
- 您要去哪？ - 去EIsinore
- Where are you heading? - To Elsinore.
- 我劝你最好别去 - 为什么呢？
- I'd advise against a trip like that. - Why, if I may ask?
瘟疫已经从海岸蔓延过来 上万人因此死掉了
The plague is going down the coast. People are dying in their ten thousands.
- 祸不单行啊 - 跟着我穿过树林
- Trouble always brings his brother. - Follow me through the woods.
你可以呆在我这或者去东海岸 那样就安全了
You can stay at my estate or follow the east coast. You'll be safer.
这些是木草莓，长在山上
They're wood strawberries. They grow on the hill.
我从没见过这么大的 闻上去真香
I never seen them so big. Smell how fragrant they are.
- 请用吧 - 非常感谢
- Enjoy the fare. - I thank you respectfully.
我想你的建议很好，但我还要考虑一下
I think your suggestion is good, but I must consider first.
能有同伴一起穿过树林应该很好
It would be nice to have company through the wood.
我听说那里充斥着幽灵，魔鬼和小偷
It's full of ghosts, devils and thieves. So I heard.
我想那是不错，不过我必须考虑
I said it wasn't bad, but I must consider it.
斯卡离开后，我就是剧团的负责人
Since Skat left, I'm responsible for the troupe.
- 我是老板了 - 我是老板
- I've become the manager, after all. - "I've become the manager, after all."
- 你喜欢草莓吗？ - 他救了我的命
- Would you like strawberries? - That man saved my life.
- 坐下和我们一起吧 - 约瑟夫骑士很慷慨
- Sit down and join us. - The knight's Jons conveys his thanks.
- 哦，这可真好 - 只是短暂的
- Oh, it's so nice. - For a short while.
总是这样，每天都很相似
Almost always. One day is much like the next.
没什么奇怪的 夏天总是好过冬天
Not so strange. Summer is better than winter -
因为你不会受冻 但是春天是最好的
- because you don't freeze. But spring is the very best.
我写了一首有关春天的诗 我去取我的鲁特琴
I wrote a poem about spring. I'll fetch my lute.
别这样，约瑟夫，也许我们 的客人不喜欢你的诗
Not now, Jof. Our guests might not be entertained by your verses.
- 拜托，我自己写歌 - 你说的对
- Please. I write songs myself. - There you are.
我有首有关一条不贞节的鱼的歌 你们一定没有听过
I have one about an unchaste fish you may not have heard.
你们也听不到
You won't hear it, either.
很多人不理解我的艺术 我也不想折磨任何人
Some people don't appreciate my art and I don't wish to torment anyone.
- 烦恼总是这么多 - 当你结婚后会好很多
- One worries so much. - It's better when you are a couple.
- 你有爱过谁吗？ - 是的…
- Don't you have anyone? - Yes...
- 她现在在干什么？ - 我不知道
- What is she doing now? - I don't know.
你看起来很严肃 她是你的甜心吗？
You look so solemn. Was she your sweetheart?
我们是新婚，在一起玩，一起笑
We were newlyweds, played together, laughed quite a lot.
我写歌赞美她的眼睛，鼻子 和美丽的耳朵
I wrote songs to her eyes, her nose, her exquisite, small ears.
我们去打猎，晚上跳舞 生活得非常充实
We went on hunts. In the evening we danced, the house was full of life.
你还要些草莓吗？
Would you like some strawberries?
信仰是沉重的负担，你知道吗？
Faith is a heavy burden, do you know that?
就像一个躲在黑暗中的爱人 无论你怎样呼唤，都不会出现
It's like loving someone in the dark who never comes, no matter how you call.
但是当我坐在这
和你和你丈夫一起时 所有这些都变得虚幻了
But all of that seems unreal when I sit here with you and your husband.
它突然变得无关紧要
It's suddenly insignificant.
你现在看起来不那么严肃了
Now you don't look so solemn.
我会记住这一刻，这祥和的黄昏…
I will remember this moment. The stillness and the dusk...
还有野草莓和牛奶
The bowl of wild strawberries, of milk...
你在暮色中的脸庞…
Your faces in the evening light...
米克尔在安睡，约瑟夫弹着鲁特琴
Mikael lying asleep, Jof with his lute.
我会竭力记住我们说的每句话
I will try and remember what we spoke of.
我会小心地珍藏这段记忆
And I will carry this memory between my hands...
就像捧着满满一碗牛奶一般小心
...as carefully as if it were a bowl brimming with freshly milked milk.
这会是我生命中闪光的一刻…
And this will be a sign for me... and greatly fulfilling.
我一直在等
I have been waiting.
对不起，我有事耽误了
Excuse me, I was somewhat delayed.
我已经调整了战术
As I've given away my strategy, I will retreat.
随便，该你走了
Go ahead. It's your move.
- 为什么你看起来这么开心 - 那是我的秘密
- Why do you look so pleased? - That's my secret.
事实上，我要吃掉你的骑士了
Naturally. I will take your knight now.
当然
You were right to.
- 你在骗我？ - 当然，你掉进了陷阱
- Have you tricked me? - Of course, you fell into the trap.
我控制了局势
I put you in check.
- 你在笑什么？
- 没什么，想办法保你的国王吧
- What are you laughing at? - No matter. Save your king instead.
- 你太骄傲了 - 我们的游戏很有趣
- You are quite arrogant. - Our game amuses me.
该你走了，快点，我赶时间
It's your move. Be quick, I'm in a hurry.
我知道你忙，但是你逃不了比赛
I know you are busy, but you won't avoid our game. It will take its time.
你会和小丑一起穿越树林？
You're travelling with the jesters through the woods?
那个叫约瑟夫和米亚的… 还有一个小孩？
The two called Jof and Mia... who have a little son?
你为什么问这个？
Why do you ask?
没什么…
No reason...
- 你看到乔恩了吗？我们该走了 - 我想他在旅馆
- Have you seen Jons? We must go. - I believe he's in the inn.
天哪，这不是铁匠吗？
Good heavens. If it isn't Plog the blacksmith.
- 晚上好 - 你自己一个人在哭？
- Evening. - Are you snivelling all alone?
是啊，就像一只无助的小兔子
Yes, the blacksmith's sobbing and wailing like a soaked rabbit.
- 还是因为老婆？ - 是的，我找不到她
- Still the wife? - Yes, I haven't found her.
是啊，有女人是地狱没有她们还是地狱
Yes, it's hell with women and hell without them.
最好就是趁最好的时候杀掉她们
Logical to kill them when it's at its best.
- 洗洗涮涮 - 大哭的孩子和湿盘子
- Henpecking and swills. - Screaming babies and wet nappies.
- 尖尖的指甲和怨毒的叫骂 - 丈母娘就像魔鬼的姑母
- Sharp nails and malice. - The Devil's aunt as mother-in-law.
- 什么时候才能入睡… - 另一个世界…
- Then when you're going to sleep... - Another tune...
眼泪，诉苦，和满肚子的牢骚
Tears, complaints and laments by the sackfull.
- 为什么你不吻我？ - 为什么你不唱歌？
- "Why don't you kiss me?" - "Why don't you sing?"
- 为什么你不再像以前那样爱我？ - 为什么你不看看我的新衣服
- "Why don't you love me like before?" - "Why don't you eye my new shift?"
- 你只会转过身去打呼噜 - 哦，见鬼…
- "You just turn your back and snore." - Oh, hell...
哦，见鬼…她走了！高兴点！
Oh, hell... She's gone now! Be happy!
我要用我的火钳夹住他们的鼻子
I'm going to pinch them in the nose with my pliers.
我要用我的锤子砸碎他们的胸膛
I'm going to pound them on the chest with the little hammer.
我要砸烂他们的脑袋
I'm going to crack them lightly on the head with the sledgehammer.
看看，他振作起来了！
Look, he's blubbering again!
- 或许我爱她 - 或许你爱她？
- Maybe I love her. - Maybe you love her?
听着，你这笨蛋 爱只是性欲的另一种说法
Listen, you moron, love is another word for lust -
只是欲望加上无休止的谎言和欺骗
- plus lust, plus lust, plus a lot of deception, falsehoods and trickery.
- 但是真的很伤人 - 爱是最可怕的瘟疫
- But it hurts anyway. - Love is the blackest of all plagues.
如果沉溺其中或许会有欢乐 但是稍纵即逝
If you died from it there'd be some joy. But it almost always passes.
- 不，我的还没有消失 - 哦，你的也消失了
- No, mine won't pass. - Oh, yes, yours too!
只有少数几个傻瓜才会为爱而死
There are only a few poor dullards now and then who die of love.
如果在这个不完美的世界上 所有的东西都是不完美的
If all is imperfect in this imperfect world, then love is most imperfect -
那么爱就是最不完美的
- in it's perfect imperfection.
你真幸运――能相信这些废话
You're lucky to have such a fluid tongue that you believe your own twaddle.
相信？谁说的 我只不过喜欢给出好建议
Believe? Who said I did? But I love giving good advice.
要求一个却得到两个 我是个好学的青年
Ask for one and you get two. So I'm actually a learned chap.
乔恩，我能和你一起穿过树林吗？
Jons! Can I follow you through the woods?
我太孤独了，也不想回家听他们嘲笑我
I'm so Ionely and don't want to go home as they all laugh at me.
除非你别再哭了，否则我们不会带你
As long as you don't sob all the time or we'll leave you.
乔恩
Jons!
- 我的小兄弟… - 小心，乔恩！
- My little brother... - Watch out, Jons!
- 他只想打架 - 他在哭
- He just wants to fight. - He's sobbing now.
我如果伤到你，我很抱歉 但是我就是这个脾气
I'm really sorry if I harmed you, but I have such a temper.
抓住我的手
Take my hand.
- 让我拥抱你吧，小兄弟 - 等等吧
- Let me embrace you, little brother. - A little later, maybe.
我们真的很忙，谢谢
We're actually in a hurry. Thanks.
啊，我看到了谁？ 谁在森林的边缘若隐若现…
Ah, what do I see? Who is it looms out of the edge of the forest -
如果不是我最爱的演员还会是谁！
- if not My Most Treasured with attached actor!
小心！
Watch out!
你肯定就是那个伤害 我的Kunigunda的脏铁匠
You must be the dirty blacksmith that humiliated my beloved Kunigunda.
- 你叫她什么？ - Kunigunda，你聋了吗？
- What did you say her name was? - Kunigunda. Are you deaf?
她叫莉萨，笨莉萨 小偷莉萨，或者妓女莉萨
Her names's Lisa. Lisa Daft or Sloven or Tart.
- 轻佻的莉萨 - 哦上帝，他真粗鲁
- Drawerless Hussy or Arse Lisa. - Goodness, he's base!
总好过色情，不像你 你这个贱女人
Just good at sleaze, not unlike yourself, you gilded bawd-pudding.
- 天哪，他太过分了
- 你这个恶心丑陋的臭杂种
- Oh, he's base! - You awful, cropped bastard...
如果我是你
...of seven mangey mongrels, if I were in your infested rags -
我就会因为羞愧去撞墙
- I'd be afflicted by such boundless shame -
我会因为自己生的 如此恶心而自甘堕落
- that I'd free nature from my embarrassing countenance.
- 小心点，你这个… - 娘娘腔
- Watch out, you perfumed... - Powder-puff.
娘娘腔… 我会让你死得很难看
Powder-puff... that I don't let off a fart -
送你去杂耍人的地狱
- that will assign you to the juggler's inferno in a flash -
- 在那你们可以坐在一起… - 自言自语…
- where you can sit together and... - Read soliloquies...
自言自语直到魔鬼耳朵都长茧子
Read soliloquies to one another until dust forms in the Devil's ears.
小心点，我会捅破你的肠胃 让它们从你的耳朵流出来
Careful I don't poke your belly so your intestines flow out your ears.
我会痛扁你，让你再不能表演 那些乱七八糟的东西
Careful I don't smack you so you can't even play for Turks and cannibals.
你在笑什么？这很严肃
What are you lauging at? This is serious.
在南方有一种长的很像人的动物叫猿
In southern lands there is a man-like animal called an ape.
- 那又怎么了？ - 只是…
- What of it? - Just that...
- 普洛戈，我的普洛戈 - 什么？
- Plog, my only Plog. - What?
- 什么？ - 亲爱的普洛戈，原谅我吧
- What? - Darling Plog, forgive me everything.
- 她会在一分钟内开始哭
- 我不得不哭，这简直太可怕了
- She'll start crying in a minute. - I have to cry. It's awful.
那个男人欺骗了我，你不会相信的
That man deceived me so badly, you won't believe.
- Kunigunda，如果真相大白的话… - 现在好戏上演了
- Kunigunda, if the truth will out... - And now for his favourite dishes.
普洛戈，我们回家后我给你做饭…
Plog, when we get home I'll make dumplings for you -
做你最爱吃的甘蓝团子
- with mashed turnips and lingonberries which is your favourite.
- 不是吗，普洛戈？
- 是，但是我必须先杀了他
- Isn't that so, Plog? - Yes, but I have to kill him first.
对，杀了他，他真该死
Yes, kill him. Kill him really properly.
- 我一点都不喜欢他
- 上帝啊，为什么你要创造女人
- I don't like him at all anymore. - God, why did you give us woman?
你知道他吗？假胡子和假牙
You know what he is? Just a false beard, false teeth -
假笑和预演好的台词，一个绣花枕头
- false smiles, rehearsed intonation and empty as a jar.
- 杀了他 - 我亲爱的普洛戈
- Go ahead and kill him. - My dear Plog...
如果你以为那就是所谓的我
那你就错了
If you thought I'd defend my so-called reality you're mistaken.
- 杀了我吧，我谢谢你 - 你在说什么？
- Kill me. I'll thank you... afterwards. - What are you saying?
他开始混乱了，已经胜利了一半
He's created confusion. Already a half victory.
- 做点什么，别光站在那 - 我恐怕杀不了他
- Do something, don't just stand there! - He has to fight or I can't kill him.
他必须激怒我才行
He has to provoke me so I get angry like before.
亲爱的朋友，我要把这匕首刺进胸膛
Dear friend, I lower this dagger to my breast.
那样我的形象就会完全改观
And my reality will quickly transform into a new, solid reality.
我的尸体会说明一切
The absolute manifestation of the corpse.
等等…我不是那个意思
Wait... I didn't mean it like that.
我原谅你，Kunigunda，再会了 我的朋友们，时常想想我吧
I forgive you, Kunigunda. Farewell, my friend, pray for me sometime.
哦，天哪…
Oh, dear... Oh, dear...
我真的不是那个意思 我已经开始喜欢他了
I didn't mean it like that. I started to really like him.
他绝对死了，我从没见过这样的死法
He's absolutely dead. I've almost never seen such a dead actor.
真是伤心啊 尽管他只是一点小小的要求
It's really sad, although he wanted it himself, poor thing.
- 而我却和她结婚…
- 可是你的小莉萨回来了
- And I'm married to her... - Well, you got your little Lisa back.
- 你不开心吗？ - 乔恩，准确的说…
- Aren't you happy? - Jons, in the strictest confidence...
- 生命是不是太…
- 是的，不过别想它了
- Isn't life quite... - Yes, it is. But don't think about it.
真是疯狂，那就是为什么
It's mad, that's what it is.
表演精彩极了 我如果不是演员就什么也不是了
That was a good performance. I'm nothing if not a good actor.
我会找棵树爬上去
I'll find a tree and climb it.
那样就没有熊，狼 或者幽灵能抓到我了
So no bears, wolves or ghosts can get hold of me.
我明天要去找约瑟夫和米亚 我们一起去All Saints节
I'll find Jof and Mia tomorrow, then we'll go to the All Saints Festival.
我会为自己唱首歌
I'll sing a song to myself. "I'm a little bird who sings how I want"
森林里的工匠…真好啊
Craftsmen in the forest... How nice.
天哪，这是我的树 你居然锯它！
By God, it's my tree they're sawing down!
嘿，你这个混蛋！ 你干嘛锯我的树？
Hey, you dozy cockerel! What are you doing to my tree?
你不会回答吗？
礼貌真是不值钱，你是谁？
Can't you answer? Courtesy is cheap. Who are you?
我锯倒树的时候，你的大限就到了
I'm sawing down your tree as your time is up.
- 这不可能，我没时间 - 你没时间吗？
- It's not possible. I don't have time. - Haven't you got time?
- 我要去演出
- 因为死亡，它已经被取消了
- I've got a performance. - It's cancelled. Because of a death.
- 我的合同！ - 取消了
- My contract! - Annulled.
- 我的家人和孩子…
- 斯卡特，你该感到羞愧
- My family and my children... - Shame on you, Skat!
我是很羞愧，羞愧…
I am ashamed, I'm ashamed...
没有什么特赦之类的？ 一些有关演员的特别规定？
Aren't there any acquittals? Any special rules for actors?
不，没有
No, not in this case.
没有漏洞，没有例外
No loopholes, no exceptions...
月亮从云后升起来了
The moon just came out from behind the clouds.
很好，我们可以更清楚地看路了
Good. We'll see the road better.
- 我不喜欢今晚的月亮 - 森林太安静了
- I don't like the moon tonight. - The trees are so still.
- 那是因为没有风 - 他是说它太寂静了
- That's because there isn't any wind. - He means they are very still.
完全的寂静
It's completely quiet.
- 起码我们能听到狐狸的声音 - 或者是猫头鹰
- If we at least heard a fox. - Or an owl.
或者除了我们之外的人的声音
Or a human voice. Beside one's own...
- 你去哪？ - 找个树桩
- Where are you going? - To the stake.
我知道，是那个巫婆 为什么要在午夜烧死她？
I see, it's the witch. Why burn her in the middle of the night?
- 人们现在都很缺少娱乐 - 安静点
-People lack amusement nowadays. - Quiet, by all the dev... saints.
- 她身体里有魔鬼
- 那你们可是八个勇敢的小伙子
- She has the Devil with her. - Then you men are eight brave men.
我们有酬劳，是自愿干这个的
Well, we're paid. The task was voluntary.
你听得到吗?
Do you hear me?
- 他们说你为魔鬼工作 - 你为什么问这个？
- They say you worked with the Devil. - Why do you ask that?
不是好奇，是很私人的原因
Not out of curiosity, but for highly personal reasons.
- 我也想见见他 - 为什么？
- I also want to meet him. - Why?
我想问问他有关上帝的事
I want to ask him about God.
他一定知道的，如果他是魔鬼
He must know. He if anyone.
- 只要你想你就能见到 - 怎么样做？
- You can see him when you want. - How?
那你就必须照我的话做
But then you must do as I say.
看着我的眼睛
Look into my eyes.
你看到了什么？你看到他了吗？
Well? What do you see? Do you see him?
我看到你眼睛里有一点点恐惧
I see a rigid fear in your eyes.
别的没什么了
Nothing else.
没有人，什么都没有…
No one, nothing... no one...
不…
No...
他不也站在你的身后吗？
Isn't he standing behind your back either?
不，那什么也没有
No. There's nothing here.
但他总是伴随着我 我只需要伸出手就能感觉到他
But he's with me everywhere. I only need to put out my hand and I feel his.
他现在还和我一起，火伤害不了我
He with me now as well. The fire won't hurt me.
- 他这么说的吗？ - 我知道
- Has he said so? - I know.
我知道，你肯定会在某处看到他
I know, I know. You must see him somewhere, you must!
牧师也可以看到他，这些人也可以
The priest had no trouble seeing him, nor the troops.
他们很怕他，他们甚至不敢碰我
They're so scared of him they don't even dare to touch me.
- 为什么你们夹她的手？ - 不是我们干的
- Why have you crushed her hands? - It's not us.
- 谁？ - 问那边的僧侣吧
- Who? - Ask the monk over there.
你对那女孩做了什么？
What have you done to the girl?
你总是不停地发问吗？
Do you never cease asking?
是的…从不停止
No... I never cease.
但是你得不到回答
But you don't get any answer.
我想过杀了守卫 但是没用的，她快死了
I thought about killing the guard, but it doesn't help. She's almost dead.
我告诉你小心点！别离她太近
I told you to watch out! Don't go near to her.
吃了这个，痛苦就会消失了
Eat this and the pain will go.
- 她看到了什么？你知道吗？ - 她不会再有痛苦了
- What's she see? Can you answer? - She's not in pain anymore.
你没有回答我的问题 谁来照顾那些孩子？
You're not answering my question. Who will take care of that child?
是天使，上帝，撒旦
还是什么人都没有？
Is it the angels or God or Satan or just emptiness?
- 没有人，先生… - 不能这样！
- Emptiness, Sire... - It can't be so!
看看她的眼睛
她可怜地意识到一些东西
Look at her eyes. Her poor consciousness is perceiving something.
- 月下的虚无 - 不…
- Emptiness under the moon. - No...
我们只能无能为力的站在这里 看着她看到的一切
We stand powerless with hanging arms, as we see what she sees.
我们和她有着同样的恐惧
Our fear and hers are the same.
那小孩…我受不了了…受不了了
That little child... I can't be bothered, I can't be bothered...
He sings so beautifully of Jesus Christ
There is great joy in heaven
黎明就要来了 尽管有那见鬼的火刑架
The dawn will break soon. Yet the heat hangs like a damp blanket.
我好怕
I'm so scared.
我们知道有些事会降临
但不知道是什么
We feel something is going to happen to us, but we don't know what it is.
- 或许是末日 - 末日
- Maybe the final day. - The final day.
你有水吗？能给我些吗？
Haven't you got any water? Can you give me some water?
- 我染上了瘟疫
- 就在树桩那边别过来！
- I've got the plague. - Keep to the other side of the stump!
我害怕死亡，我不想死，不想死！
I'm scared of dying. I don't want to die, I don't want to!
你们不能可怜可怜我？帮帮我…
Can't you take pity on me? Help me...
至少和我说话！
At least talk to me!
没用的，没用的
It doesn't help. It doesn't help.
我知道那没用
I know it doesn't help at all.
我要死了，我…我…
I'm going to die. I... I...
我将会怎么样？
你们就不能安慰我一下？
What's going to happen to me? Can't you even comfort me?
你们没有一点怜悯之心吗？
你们难道看不到我…
Haven't you got any mercy? Can't you see that I...
没人帮我吗？我不能有点水吗？
Is there no help? Can't I have any water?
毫无意义，那毫无意义
It's meaningless. It's completely meaningless.
我说了那毫无意义
I said it's meaningless.
- 救救我！ - 你听不到我说什么吗？
- Help me! - Can't you hear I'm comforting you?
- 我们能结束游戏吗？ - 该你走
- Shall we conclude our game? - It's your move.
- 我吃了你的皇后 - 我看不到
- I took your queen. - I didn't see that.
米亚…我看到一些可怕的事 一些无法形容的事
Mia... I see something terrible, something almost unspeakable.
- 你看到了什么？ - 那个骑士在下棋
- What do you see? - The knight is playing chess.
- 我也看到啦，没什么可怕的 - 你看到他在和谁下吗？
- I see that too. It's not so terrible. - You see who he's playing with?
- 他自己，别这样吓唬我 - 不，不，他不是一个人
-He's alone. Don't scare me like that. - No, no. He's not alone.
- 那是谁？ - 死神，他在和死神下棋
- Who is it? - Death. He's playing Death himself.
- 别那么说 - 我们必须逃走了
- Don't say that. - We must try and get away.
- 我们不能 - 必须走
- We can't. - We must try.
他们正全神贯注的下棋 如果我们悄悄走开，他们不会知道的
They're so engrossed in their game, if we leave quietly they won't notice.
该你走了
It's you move, Antonius Block.
你对我们的游戏失去兴趣了？
Have you lost interest in our game?
失去兴趣？恰恰相反…
Lost interest? On the contrary...
你看来很焦虑 你隐瞒了什么吗？
You look anxious. Are you concealing something?
- 什么东西都逃不过你的眼睛，是吗？ - 没有
- Nothing escapes you. Not so? - Nothing escapes me.
- 没人能逃得过我
- 是的，我很焦虑
- No one escapes me. - It is true I'm anxious.
你害怕了
You are scared.
我忘了这些棋子都放在哪了
I forget where the pieces were.
但是我还没有忘
But I haven't forgotten.
你别想轻易跑掉
You won't get away that easily.
- 我看到些有趣的东西 - 你看到了什么？
- I see something interesting now. - What do you see?
你在下一手里会被将死
You will be checkmate in the next move.
是的…
That's true...
- 在你多活的这些日子里有什么收获吗？ - 是的，有收获
- Did you profit from your respite? - Yes, I did.
那很好，我现在就走
That pleases me. I will leave you now.
当我们再见的时候 你和你周围的一切都结束了
When we meet again you and your entourage's time will be over.
- 那你会讲出你的秘密吗？ - 我没有秘密
- And you'll reveal your secrets? - I carry no secrets.
那么说，你什么也不知道？
So you know nothing?
我是无知的
I am unknowing.
- 你看到那奇怪的光了吗？ - 那是随着黎明而来的风暴
- Do you see that strange light? - It's the storm coming with the dawn.
是别的东西，很可怕的 你听到隆隆声了吗?
It's something else, something terrible. You hear the rumbling?
- 很可能是雨 - 不，不是雨
- It's probably the rain. - No, it's not the rain.
他看到我们了，跟着我们 他追上我们了
He's seen us, followed us, he's caught up to us, he's coming at us!
进马车里去，米亚 我们进去，快点
Get in the wagon, Mia. Let's get in, quickly!
死亡精灵要通过这里 米亚，死亡精灵
It's the angel of death passing by, Mia. The angel of death.
- 而且他非常大 - 你觉得冷吗？
- And he's very big... - Do you feel how cold it is?
我听回来的十字军战士说 你们在回来的路上
I heard from returning crusaders that you were on your way home.
我一直在等你 其他人都逃走了，躲避瘟疫
I've waited for you. All the others have fled the plague.
你不认识我了吗？
Don't you recognize me anymore?
你也变了
You've also changed.
现在我看着你
Now I can see it's you.
你的眼睛…
Somewhere in your eyes...
你的脸，还隐藏着恐惧
Somewhere in your face, but hidden and frightened...
就像许多年前出征的男孩一样
...is that boy that set off all those years ago.
那已经结束了，我有点累了
It's over now and I'm a little tired.
- 你很后悔回来？ - 不
- Do you regret your journey? - No.
我没有后悔，只是有点累了
I don't regret anything. But I'm a little tired.
我能看出来…
I can see...
我的朋友在这
My friends are there.
叫他们进来，我会架桌子准备早餐
Ask them to come in. I'll set the table for breakfast.
【和合本 启示录8:1】
“羔羊揭开第七印的时候……”
"And when the Lamb opened the seventh seal"-
“天上寂静……”
-"there was in heaven a silence"-
“约有二刻”
-"which lasted about the space of half an hour."
【和合本 启示录8:6】
“拿着七枝号的七位天使……”
"And the seven angels who had the seven trumpets"-
“就预备要吹”
-"prepared themselves to sound."
【和合本 启示录8:7】
“第一位天使吹号”
"The first angel sounded"-
“就有雹子与火搀着血”
-"and there followed hail and fire mingled with blood."
“丢在地上”
"And they were cast upon the earth."
“地的三分之一”
"And the third part of the earth was burnt up"-
“和树的三分之一被烧了”
- "and the third part of trees was burnt up"-
“一切的青草也被烧了”
-"and all green grass was burnt up".
【和合本 启示录8:8】
“第二位天使吹号”
"And the second angel sounded"-
“就有彷佛火烧着的大山”
-"and as it were a great mountain burning with fire"-
“扔在海中”
-"was cast into the sea."
“海的三分之一变成血”
"And the third part of the sea became blood."
有人在那吗？
Was there anyone there?
没有，先生…我看不到任何人
No, Sire... I saw no one.
【和合本 启示录8:10】
“第三位天使吹号”
"And the third angel sounded."
“就有烧着的大星”
"And there fell a great star from heaven"-
“好像火把从天上落下来”
-"burning as it were a lamp."
【和合本 启示录8:11】
“这星名叫‘茵c’”
"And the name of the star is called Wormwood."
你好，尊贵的先生
Good day, noble Sire.
我是卡琳，骑士的妻子 请您进来坐吧
I am Karin, wife of the knight. I bid you a courteous welcome to my home.
我是个铁匠，如果要我说，我是个好人
I am a blacksmith by trade and quite good if I say so myself.
我妻子，莉萨 行屈膝礼，莉萨
My wife, Lisa. Curtsey for the honourable Sire, Lisa.
她有些难缠，我们也吵过一两次…
She's a little difficult at times and we've had a little affray -
但是比大多数人好
- but no worse than most people.
在黑暗中我们呼唤主 主啊，怜悯我们吧
In our darkness we call out to you Lord. Oh God, have mercy on us.
因为我们渺小，懦弱和无知
For we are small, afraid and without knowledge.
你要我们生活在黑暗里
In that darkness where you claim to reside, where we probably all reside -
你会发现没有人会听你的抱怨 或被你的惩罚所动摇
- you'll find no one that listens to your complaint or is moved by your suffering.
- 擦干你的眼泪，照照你自己 - 主啊，你无处不在…
- Dry your tears, mirror your apathy. - God, you that exist somewhere...
那必然有一处能让你宽恕我们
...that must exist somewhere, have mercy on us.
我有一种草药能使你 永远摆脱烦恼，现在太晚了
I had a herb to purge your anxiety over the eternal. Now it's too late.
感受这最后的生命时刻吧
Feel in this final minute the triumph of rolling your eyes and moving your toes.
- 安静…安静
- 我会安静的，但是是无声的抗议
- Quiet... Quiet. - I'll be quiet, but under protest!
结束了…
It is finished...
米亚！我能看到他们，米亚
Mia! I can see them, Mia.
我能看到他们 就在暴风雨的天空下
I can see them. Over there under the storm-laden skies.
他们都在那，铁匠，还有莉萨
They're all there. The blacksmith and Lisa -
骑士，瑞瓦，乔恩，还有斯卡…
- the knight and Raval, Jons and Skat...
而那冷酷的主人，死神 邀请他们跳舞
And the grim master, Death, invites them to dance.
他要他们手拉手排成一排跳舞
He wants them to hold hands and dance in a long line.
而主人用长镰和沙漏指引他们
And the grim master leads with scythe and hourglass.
斯卡背后背着他的七弦琴
Skat brings up the rear with his lyre.
他们走了
They move away, away from the dawn -
跳着庄严的舞步，走向黑暗的国度
- in a solemn dance, away to the dark country.
雨水洗净他们的脸庞
Whilst the rain washes over their faces -
冲去他们脸上的泪水
- cleans their cheeks of tears of salt.
你和你白日梦啊…
You and your dreams and visions...